<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" 
             type="application/xml" 
             schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="en">Of Fear</title>
            <author xml:id="MM"><persName>Michel de Montaigne</persName></author>
            <editor role="editor"><persName>William Carew Hazlitt</persName></editor>
            <editor role="translator"><persName>Charles Cotton</persName></editor>
            <sponsor>
               <orgName xml:id="GP" ref="https://gutenberg.org/">Project Gutenberg</orgName>
            </sponsor>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <distributor>
               <orgName ref="#GP">Project Gutenberg</orgName>
            </distributor>
            <address>
               <name type="foundation">Project Gutenberg Literary Archive Foundation</name>
               <postBox>PO Box 16327</postBox>
               <name type="city">Salt Lake City</name>
               <name type="country">United States Of America</name>
               <postCode>84116</postCode>
            </address>
            <idno type="URL">https://gutenberg.org/cache/epub/3600/pg3600-images.html</idno>
            <date when="2004-10-26">October 26, 2004</date>
            <availability status="free" xml:lang="en">
               <p>This ebook is for the use of anyone anywhere in the United States and most other
                  parts of the world at no cost and with almost no restrictions whatsoever. You may
                  copy it, give it away or re-use it under the terms of the Project Gutenberg
                  License included with this ebook or online at www.gutenberg.org. If you are not
                  located in the United States, you will have to check the laws of the country where
                  you are located before using this eBook.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <title>Essays</title>
                  <author sameAs="#MM"><persName>Michel de Montaigne</persName></author>
                  <editor role="translator"><persName>Charles Cotton</persName></editor>
                  <editor role="editor"><persName>William Carew Hazlitt</persName></editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Kensington</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1877">1877</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <extent>1453 p.</extent>
               </monogr>
               <citedRange unit="chapter">17</citedRange>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>


   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
         <head type="mainTitle">"CHAPTER XVII——OF FEAR"</head>
         <p> 
            <cit>
               <quote xml:id="cit1" xml:lang="la" rend="italic"> Obstupui, steteruntque comae et vox
                  aucibus haesit. </quote>
               <lb/>
               
               
               <quote xml:lang="en" sameAs="#cit1"> I was amazed, my hair stood on end, and my voice
                  stuck in my throat.</quote>  <lb/>
               <bibl>
                  <author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1398">Virgil</author>, <title>Aeneid</title>, <citedRange unit="volume"
                     >2</citedRange>, <citedRange unit="line">774.</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </cit>
         </p> 
         <p> I am not so good a naturalist (as they call it) as to discern by what secret springs
            fear has its motion in us; but, be this as it may, ‘tis a strange passion, and such a
            one that the physicians say there is no other whatever that sooner dethrones our
            judgment from its proper seat; which is so true, that I myself have seen very many
            become frantic through fear; and, even in those of the best settled temper it is most
            certain that it begets a terrible astonishment and confusion during the fit.</p>
         <p>I omit the vulgar sort, to whom it one while represents their great-grandsires risen out
            of their graves in their shrouds, another while werewolves, nightmares, and chimaeras;
            but even amongst soldiers, a sort of men over whom, of all others, it ought to have the
            least power, how often has it converted flocks of sheep into armed squadrons, reeds and
            bullrushes into pikes and lances, friends into enemies, and the French white cross into
            the red cross of Spain! </p>
         <p>When <rs type=" person" xml:id="MonsieurdeBourbon"
               ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q506466"><persName>Monsieur de Bourbon</persName>
            </rs> took <rs type="place" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q220" xml:id="Rome"
                  ><placeName>Rome </placeName>
            </rs> ,—[In <rs type="Event" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q465627"
               xml:id="SigeofRome"> 1527</rs> ]—an ensign who was upon guard at <rs type="Place"
               xml:id="CastelSanpietroRomano" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q242120"
                  ><placeName> Borgo San Pietro</placeName>
            </rs> was seized with such a fright upon the first alarm, that he threw himself out at a
            breach with his colours upon his shoulder, and ran directly upon the enemy, thinking he
            had retreated toward the inward defences of the city, and with much ado, seeing <rs
               type="person" sameAs="#MonsieurdeBourbon"> Monsieur de Bourbon</rs> ’s people, who
            thought it had been a sally upon them, draw up to receive him, at last came to himself,
            and saw his error; and then facing about, he retreated full speed through the same
            breach by which he had gone out, but not till he had first blindly advanced above three
            hundred paces into the open field.</p>
         <p>It did not, however, fall out so well with Captain Giulio’s ensign, at the time when St.
            Paul was taken from us by the Comte de Bures and Monsieur de Reu, for he,<pb/> being so
            astonished with fear as throw himsel, colours and all out of a porthole, was
            immediately, cut to pieces by the enemy; and in the <rs type="event" ref="#SigeofRome">
               same sige </rs> , it was a very memorable fear that so seized, contracted, and froze
            up the heart of a gentleman, that he sank down, stone-dead, in the breach, without any
            manner of wound or hurt at all. </p>
         <p> The like madness does sometimes push on a whole multitude; for in <rs type="event"
               xml:id="RomanCampaignGermania"
               ref="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roman_campaigns_in_Germania_(12_BC_%E2%80%93_AD_16)"
               > one of the encounters </rs> that <rs type="person" xml:id="Germanicus"
               ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q191039">
               <persName> Germanicus </persName>
            </rs> had with the Germans, two great parties were so amazed with fear that they ran two
            opposite ways, the one to the same place from which the other had fled. —<bibl>
               [<author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2161">Tacit</author> , <title>Annal</title>
               <biblScope unit="volume">I </biblScope>. <biblScope unit="page"
               >63</biblScope>]</bibl>— Sometimes it adds wings to the heels, as in the two first:
            sometimes it nails them to the ground, and fetters them from moving; as we read of the
               <rs type="person" xml:id="EmperorTheophilus"
               ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q60199">Emperor theophilus</rs> , who, in a battle
            he lost against the Agarenes, was so astonished and stupefied that he had no power to
            fly </p>
           <p>
            <cit>
               <quote xml:lang="la" rend="italics" xml:id="cit2"> Adeo pavor etiam auxilia
                  formidat</quote> <lb/>

               <quote xml:lang="en" sameAs="#cit2"> So much does fear dread even the means of
                  safety. </quote>
               <bibl>
                  <author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q5959"> Quintus Curtius Rufus</author>, <title>Historiae</title>, <citedRange
                     unit="volume">2</citedRange>, <citedRange unit="chapter">2.</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </cit> 
            </p>
         <p>
               till such time as <rs xml:id="Manuel"> Manuel </rs> , one of the principal
            commanders of his army, having jogged and shaked him so as to rouse him out of his
            trance, said to him, <said who="#Manuel" direct="true" aloud="true"> “Sir, if you will
               not follow me, I will kill you; for it is better you should lose your life than, by
               being taken, lose your empire.” </said>
            <bibl> [<author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q32052">Joannes Zonaras </author> , <title>Epitome Historiarum</title>,
               <biblScope unit="volume">III </biblScope>. </bibl>
         </p>
         <p> But fear does then manifest its utmost power when it throws us upon a valiant despair,
            having before deprived us of all sense both of duty and honour.</p>
         <p> In <rs type="event" xml:id="BattleOfTicino" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q378957"
               > the first pitched battle </rs> the Romans lost against <rs type="person"
               xml:id="Hannibal" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q36456">
               <persName> Hannibal</persName></rs> , under the Consul Sempronius, a body of ten
            thousand foot, that had taken fright, seeing no other escape for their cowardice, went
            and threw themselves headlong upon the great battalion of the enemies, which with
            marvellous force and fury they charged through and through, and routed with a very great
            slaughter of the Carthaginians, thus purchasing an ignominious flight at the same price
            they might have gained a glorious victory. <bibl> [<author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2039">Livy</author>,
                  <title>Historia</title>,
               <biblScope unit="volume">XXI </biblScope>. <biblScope unit="page"
               >56</biblScope>]</bibl></p>
         <p> The thing in the world I am most afraid of is fear, that passion alone, in the trouble
            of it, exceeding all other accidents.</p>
         <p> What affliction could be <pb/>grater or more just than that of <rs type="person"
               xml:id="Pompey" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q125414">Pompey </rs> 's friends,
            who, in his ship,were spectators of that horrible murder? Yet so it was, that the fear
            of the Egyptian vessels they saw coming to board them, possessed them with so great
            alarm that it is observed they thought of nothing but calling upon the mariners to make
            haste, and by force of oars to escape away, till being arrived at <rs type="place"
               xml:id="Tyre" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q82070"><placeName>Tyre</placeName>
            </rs> , and delivered from fear, they had leisure to turn their thoughts to the loss of
            their captain, and to give vent to those tears and lamentations that the other more
            potent passion had till then suspended.  </p>
            <p> <cit>
               <quote xml:lang="la" xml:id="cit3" rend="italics"> Tum pavor sapientiam omnem mihiex
                  animo expectorat. </quote> <lb/>

               <quote xml:lang="en" sameAs="#cit3"> Then fear drove out all intelligence from my
                  mind.</quote>
               <bibl>
                  <author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1541"> Cicero</author>,<title>Tuscolanae Disputationes</title>,<citedRange
                     unit="volume">IV</citedRange>, <citedRange unit="chapter">8</citedRange>
               </bibl>
            </cit> </p>
         

         <p>Such as have been well rubbed in some skirmish, may yet, all wounded and bloody as they
            are, be brought on again the next day to charge; but such as have once conceived a good
            sound fear of the enemy, will never be made so much as to look him in the face. </p>
         <p>Such as are in immediate fear of a losing their estates, of banishment, or of slavery,
            live in perpetual anguish, and lose all appetite and repose; whereas such as are
            actually poor, slaves, or exiles, ofttimes live as merrily as other folk.</p>
         <p>And the many people who, impatient of the perpetual alarms of fear, have hanged or
            drowned themselves, or dashed themselves to pieces, give us sufficiently to understand
            that fear is more importunate and insupportable than death itself.</p>
         <p>The Greeks acknowledged another kind of fear, differing from any we have spoken of yet,
            that surprises us without any visible cause, by an impulse from heaven, so that whole
            nations and whole armies have been struck with it.</p>
         <p> Such a one was that which brought so wonderful a desolation upon <rs type="place"
               xml:id="Carthage" ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q6343">
               <placeName>Carthage</placeName>
            </rs> , where nothing was to be heard but affrighted voices and outcries; where the
            inhabitants were seen to sally out of their houses as to an alarm, and there to charge,
            wound, and kill one another, as if they had been enemies come to surprise their city.
            All things were in disorder and fury till, with prayers and sacrifices, they had
            appeased their gods —<bibl> [<author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q171241">Diodorsu Siculus</author>,<title>Historia</title>
               <biblScope unit="volume">XV </biblScope>. <biblScope unit="page"
               >7</biblScope>]</bibl>—; and this is that they call panic terrors. <bibl>
                  [<author ref="https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q171241" >Diodorsu Siculus</author>,<title>Historia</title>
               <biblScope unit="volume"> 3 </biblScope>.<biblScope unit="page"
               >8</biblScope>]</bibl>
         </p>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
